[Music]
what's up everyone
i hope you're as excited as i am to talk
a whole bunch about muscle hypertrophy
before we get started i need to
apologize i know my voice sounds a bit
weird
i've just been dealing with a couple of
weeks of a very very nasty case of the
gains yeah i know
you loved it well if you like my friend
chris here
and you like me right every one of us
that i know is interested in some point
to maximizing their muscle gains and you
may be thinking to yourself
hey andy i know that muscle physiology
is your area of expertise you study
how muscle fibers grow shrink dye and
repair in your lab and you've been doing
that for a decade
but you may not realize i actually used
to be a competitive bodybuilder
back in the day in fact i was actually
pretty famous before there was even
instagram in those things and
i used to get fans come up to me all the
time asking me for pictures and you can
see like a good example that here this
guy right up was like hey man can i get
a double biceps picture and i'm like
sure
you know so i was kind enough to take a
picture of him with it and
um you know anyways if you
you want to actually see a picture of me
my one of my competitions all right well
here it is i was a little more tan and
just a little
a little bit more muscular in this
picture here but this is
this is a local meet that i did one time
i didn't win you know obviously
i thought i got second place so it's
pretty good
well anyways uh and humans in general
we've been interested in strength
training and gaining muscle
for a really long time in fact there's
documents suggesting that we've been
lifting muscle
or lifting weights for the purpose of
growing muscle since the 7th century
there's a really cool article here by
the famous
sport historian jan todd on the history
of barbells and dumbbells and when women
started lifting with dumbbells and
things like that that
i encourage you to explore but we've
actually been studying muscle growth
with exercise for almost 100 or over 100
years now
the first study came out in the late
1800s
by a german scientist and he actually
threw a couple of dogs
on a treadmill what he did is he
actually cut one of those sartorius
muscles out of their leg
put them on a treadmill for two months
and then looked at how much
their other assault areas grew and found
about a 50
increase in hypertrophy after just
treadmill running for a couple of months
so the point being we've spent a lot of
time and effort
as a society as scientists and as
individuals
trying to understand how to maximize
muscle growth for a very long time
and if you've been up to date with the
field or you've seen any of my previous
work
especially some of my podcasts with
barbell shrugged and stuff years ago
you may feel like you got a pretty good
grip on the science but what i want to
actually do and the reason
i'm making all these videos is we have
learned a tremendous amount in the last
three years alone
on what muscle hypertrophy actually is
what causes it
and then how to then maximize it with
your training and hypertrophy
so i've decided to do this giant video
series on all things hypertrophy
in part one like i said i'll describe
some of the newest things we've learned
in just the last couple of years in fact
several of the things i've included in
that video came out just within a month
of me filming this
so i'll talk in depth about what we know
uh scientifically
about what actually is muscle
hypertrophy what parts grow which ones
don't how much
etc part two then i'll get into the
stimuli and it causes the molecular
mechanisms
if you like the biochemistry piece uh
the molecular biology side of it
video two is your jam and then part
three is when i'll specifically get into
the eating and training to maximize
so if you just want the practical
applications you want to know how much
volume you should be hitting what order
to do your exercises in
frequency uh what type e center
concentric
drop sets pyramids which ones work
better all that stuff
that's all in video three but i actually
i think you should start with at least
video two because
you'll never really truly understand uh
how to train
to optimize growth if you don't
understand what's causing
your body to want to grow muscle in the
first place
um well what i'll also do is i'll try to
chop these up into some five-minute ones
as well but
if you want the full jam my strongest
recommendation start at one go to two
go to three and you'll all understand as
much as we could possibly give you
on all things muscle hypertrophy okay
enjoy let's have a fun ride here and
let's get a little bit more
jacked all right maybe i should stop i
don't know when i look better
welcome back everyone this is part two
of my epic
three-part series on all the newest
latest
most groundbreaking research available
on all things skeletal muscle
hypertrophy
now if you're a super muscle nerd and
you're thinking part two
i missed part one go back and check that
out now
i cover all the basics of the physiology
the the structure what part of the
muscle grows
what have we learned in the last one two
and even three years about
where what areas grow which ones don't
why etc
that's a big long look about the detail
the microscopic macroscopic and what we
call ultrastructural
look at the muscle itself in this part
i'm going to talk about the stimulation
so what do we actually have to do what
has to happen inside our body
to cause the muscle to want to grow the
third part is when i'll get into all the
specific
practical recommendations so how to
train
what rest intervals do you use what rep
range what type of lifting
how much to eat protein all that stuff
so part one is basic physiology part two
here
is the cascade of stimulation part three
is the training and eating now
i think it's important that you watch
this one even before you watch part
three
so if you're not interested in the
physiology part cool
but i think you should watch this video
prior to jumping to video three
because you're never really going to
understand how to train unless you
understand how to
cause the signal for growth right so the
reason you grow is because something
signaled the tissue to do that
so when you understand this part it
makes part three
a lot easier so hopefully i've convinced
you to stick around if you're just
looking for the practical
recommendations
i promise i'll keep you interested for
here if you're one of my students you
don't have a choice you got to watch it
anyways
so let's go ahead and dive in and let's
start talking about
part two here stimulating muscle growth
what i really mean
i can expand on stimulating what i'm
talking about what are the signals
the sensors and stimuli that induce
skeletal muscle hypertrophy and i should
even clarify a little bit here
and i won't say this again but i'm
really talking about resistance exercise
induced muscle growth so i'm not talking
about
the other things right so you're trying
to lift weights to add some muscle
that's what we're focusing on in these
videos all right i want to start off
with with a really awesome quote from uh
an article that i'll talk about a lot
here but it
a lot in this presentation right it's
it's the muscle hypertrophy
stimuli that will induce the
hypertrophic signal transduction
and result in hypertrophy thus if we
know the actual acute stimuli
then we can measure with the goal of
identifying interventions that maximally
induces signal in other words
it's important that we just don't do
studies where one group lifts this way
and another group lifts this way
and see who got bigger we want to know
how to actually cause it especially
if we want to get to that next level of
muscle growth it's important we pay
attention to the signal
so a basic outline of what we're going
to cover in this video
will be this okay i'll talk about what
are what i call the five steps to
activate muscle growth
we'll go over the three mechanisms of
muscle hypertrophy
and what we got wrong so if any of you
following along or seen my previous
videos we've seen us talk about that
it's been something that has been around
for a while but we have a lot more
update information on those mechanisms
we'll talk about of course testosterone
and igf-1 if you're familiar with that
dom's negative eccentric and what's
called exercise-induced muscle damage
mechanoreceptors metabolic stress
hypoxia blood flow restriction
uh the pump the burn all that stuff
we'll talk about cell signaling gene
expression and protein synthesis
the 141 muscle genes that regulates are
the genes that regulate muscle growth
uh training any implications a little
bit although that's mostly in part three
and then the last one is a little bit of
magic and voodoo that you have to
understand to be able to maximize your
muscle growth
so let's go ahead and dive right into it
and start talking some biochemistry
and molecular biology all right
so in order to cause your muscles to
want to grow you have to initiate and
actually
succeed this five-step muscle growing
system and it looks like this there has
to be some sort of sufficient signal
that has to be translated into signaling
that has to induce some sort of
expression of genes and then you go
through
the protein synthesis process and none
of that matters unless you have the
critical step number five
which is a secret and i'll tell you as
the video goes on
so let's go ahead and take a look at all
these five steps in detail and let's
talk about what we know scientifically
about them
and what maybe what we don't know so
step number one is to stimulus and i
didn't say stimulant
ah get it coffee stimulant
i said stimulus what i mean by that is
if you go back and you watch
part one of our series or if you just
thought about that you realize that all
of your muscles are actually made up of
millions of individual muscle cells
and at the outskirts of that muscle is
called a sarcolemma
or what we will generally call a cell
membrane okay it's the outside
and what we know now is the vast
majority of the communication of what
happens in the cell is the result of
some stimuli hitting the cell membrane
or the outside of the sarcoma
so in this case if you want to grow
muscle something has to talk to the cell
and the best way to do that is to have
some sort of insult on the cell wall or
the cell membrane rather
right so what does that actually look
like well i'm going to take a slight
departure and i'm going to come right
back to this okay so we've got to lay a
little bit of groundwork before we can
understand what's really happening here
so back in 10 uh 2010 rather a young
strapping young scientist
named brad schoenfeld published a really
famous article at this point i think
it's been cited over a thousand times
which is
just a mega number right it's just
ridiculous and he speculated
that there was three primary mechanisms
that caused muscle growth
number one would be mechanical tension
number two metabolic stress and three
muscle damage and i'll give brad some
credit here
he this was a pretty impressive paper
and a pretty impressive hypothesis
well we've learned a lot in the next
last nine years so some of what brad
suggested was right and some of it
wasn't quite on
but he and his team actually combined
with
a couple of other folks you can see here
henny whackerhagen and henning has just
done
an incredible amount of work on the
biology
and the biochemistry of muscle
hypertrophy so
anything you read from henning is going
to be just amazing the molecular side
he's just got it crushed
so they came off the paper just recently
said okay what's the update stimuli and
sensors that cause the muscle growth so
i'd recommend you go check out this
paper if you'd like
but i'll break you down bring it down
here and give you the very short version
and here's basically what they said
we'll start off with mechanical tension
now what's that mean
well we know that the cell has what are
called mechanosensors
so these are and i'll show you what
these look like in a second but these
are sensors along that sarcolemmer cell
wall
and the prime the two primary ones kind
of within that subcategory of
mechanosensors that probably play the
biggest role in inducing muscle
hypertrophy or stimulating it are the
costumers
and the second group of one now we have
a decent amount of evidence that the
costumers are playing
a role in this mechanical separate thing
the next one is called that this
filament m torque autophagy kind of
cascade
and we don't really know what that means
yet
so this may play a role it may not
you're gonna have to check back in a few
years it's kind of undefined and it's
been tossed out there but it really
hasn't been super well described
so we're gonna have to come back on that
one for the most part though like i said
the customers are pretty well described
and we know that those are activated
with a lot of things even as simple as
something as simple as just cell
swelling so edema water gets in there
the cell gets larger
the customers kick on and starts
transducing that signal
so how is this following the mechanical
tension umbrella
we know that if you do things that are
kind of quote unquote heavy so this
would be anything greater than 30
percent of your one right max and
certainly things above 60 percent
well we know that that causes stress on
the cell wall right you're causing the
cell to contract
that's that contraction activates those
costomers and that's how mechanical
tension
lifting something heavy translates into
a cell signal
in the tissue the heavy thing causes
cell walls to contract and move
and that activates these costumers which
are the mechanical
mechanical sensors we also know that
motor unit activation is important so
one issue we have quite consistently
with the resistance exercise in
hypertrophy literature
is i'm not fully convinced that you've
activated all the muscle fibers
what's that mean well if you did say
training at 30 percent of your one rep
max even if you did the failure
we know that the higher threshold motor
units typically the bigger larger faster
fibers aren't actually activated until
you get much heavier
probably even above 80 maybe even 90 of
your 100 max
so you have a bunch of fibers that
really never got activated so one
benefit that mechanical tension has in
other words lifting heavy
over the next two like just causing
muscle damage or causing metabolic
stress
is the fact that you're increasing the
likelihood of activating more motor
units
if it's not activated it's not going to
hypertrophy so
even if you look at say comparing
mechanical tension lifting heavy
to some of the other methods which i'll
describe later you probably have a
higher likelihood of activating growth
in more total fibers
by spending some time activating those
motor units
okay uh in addition this could all
simply be a stretch
issue right so we know that stretching
itself of the
that sarcoma that cell wall can activate
those costumers and cause
a decent amount of muscle hypertrophy as
well
since we're talking about stretch we
know that can actually activate muscle
growth through a different mechanism
which is muscle damage
so by simply stretching the cell wall
you can cause damage and that alone can
activate this cascade of muscle growth
so because of that
uh we know that doms are delayed onset
muscle soreness so the soreness you have
in your muscles a day or two
after lifting is also associated with
causing some sort of
muscle hypertrophy now we have to be
careful here because
and hopefully if you've been paying
attention to any of the things i've done
the last five years or so we know that
there's only a very modest and probably
even lower than that a low correlation
between the amount of damage you get and
the amount of growth you get
so if you're going through a workout
you're thinking if i get more sore
tomorrow than i did last time
that means i'm getting more growth and
we just simply know that that's not true
so the amount of soreness you get is
only very loosely associated with how
much growth you get
okay so we want to be careful of just
chasing damage and chasing the soreness
right but muscle damage is also
associated with things like the pump
right so if you're trying to get a
bigger pump on a muscle
causing a little bit more damage then
that's it's going to be related to
muscle growth
same with edema like i said so you can
get a lot of self swelling
in fact most of the research now
suggests that's probably explaining more
of the doms than the actual like tissue
tearing i'm not really convinced that
happens a ton in normal circumstances
it's probably just the edema that's
going on there
as well as what they call
exercise-induced muscle damage
okay all of these things are in the same
umbrella of
causing some sort of physical trauma or
stress whether it be actually ruining
the myofilaments or just
causing swelling things like that and
again
that's not a direct relationship with
any of these things to muscle growth but
there is an association here pretty
clearly
and so because of that we see things
like eccentric training
um any extra range of motion training so
if you're typically not used to going to
a certain depth
or range of motion any of your joints
and that's going to induce a little bit
more muscle soreness than usual
as well as any novelty so novelty could
be again a different exercise could be a
different range of motion could be a
different rep range or
intensity that you're not used to those
all are associated with increasing the
amount of muscle damage
okay now if we finish off this concept
then
with metabolic stress this could be a
whole host of things like
hypoxia so we have recent evidence
coming out showing that this simply
being in a hypoxic state
can activate this cascade of muscle
growth
uh other things are sore because of this
that this explains why things like the
also the pump but also the burn stuff
right so you've heard people say like if
you're not getting a pump and a muscle
and it's not burning at
all you're very likely to be causing
muscle growth and that's
somewhat true right because of this
association with metabolic stress
it also explains how things like high
repetition and low rest
so you know set to 25 sets of 50 sets of
whatever with low rest intervals or the
combination
can induce a decent amount of muscle
hypertrophy
and it also explains two fun more
concepts like blood flow restriction
training
so with blood flow restriction training
the load is incredibly
light again you're talking well maybe 30
percent of your 100 max at best perhaps
even significantly lower there's very
little if any muscle damage
but yet it still enables an equal amount
if not
greater amount of muscle growth okay
and the last one there is what i call
kind of the the aerobic exercise
interval gains conflict and so if you
look again across the literature you'll
see quite a bit of actual muscle
hypertrophy as a result of just
endurance training or interval training
things like that and we now know that
that's probably because it induced a
significant amount of metabolic stress
and that in and of itself especially if
you're untrained
sedentary or poorly trained may cause
muscle growth
okay at least initially in your training
after that it won't but the initial
stuff will work okay now you may be
thinking to yourself
wait a minute what about testosterone i
as soon as you started talking about
stimulators of muscle growth
and and the things that activated
i was totally expecting you to see
testosterone where are the hormones on
this list
well it's not it doesn't work exactly
how you think it does
so clearly testosterone is anabolic and
it is a clear part of the anabolic
cascade
but it is not a linear thing so it's a
bit of a yes and no here
in other words uh say you did one
workout
and you measured your testosterone
afterwards and you did another workout
and your testosterone
was 20 higher after that workout that
will not mean you have a 20
more growth after that workout in fact
there is a very poor if any association
between the amount of testosterone
and the amount of muscle growth they are
very poorly correlated right
again if at all now what am i not saying
i'm not saying if you take your
testosterone out
that you'll still grow equally not even
close i'm also not saying that exogenous
testosterone won't increase growth it
clearly clearly clearly does
okay but you can't walk around and
measure someone's testosterone and say
okay you're going to grow more than i am
because you have more testosterone
if your normal testosterone levels are
40 higher than mine i may still be able
to grow more muscle than you do faster
it's not really relevant to the equation
right where it becomes helpful again is
the exogenous use of testosterone
because you can put in orders of
magnitude more testosterone than you
would have
endogenously so that's when it starts to
matter
so clearly again yes testosterone has a
role in
binding to the cell wall and activating
muscle growth but it's not nearly as
tight as one would think
this is we've seen this across many
domains right we've also this is exactly
why
women who have much lower testosterone
still have no problem causing muscle
hypertrophy
elderly elder folks or even middle-aged
folks who have
reduced amounts of testosterone compared
one person to the next person again
who has higher who has lower none of
those things seem to matter and they can
all have
equal amounts of resulting hypertrophy
suggesting
the testosterone is not playing that
critical role though some think it does
in the way that people think it does
okay so
moving on then uh kind of coming back to
our original point here
the first thing that has to happen is we
have to get some sort of stimulus on
that cell wall
so let's go ahead and take a look at
what that would actually be
and here you go now this is kind of the
same graphic i used in part one
to describe a muscle cell so just
imagine that being a muscle cell
well along the outside of the wall the
sarcoma there you've got different
receptors and i've got different colors
here
and we're going to take a look at these
in more detail so let's imagine you had
some green
pink and then black receptors say the
ones that are in green
are your mechano sensors and those
things again are going to send your
stretch
or your muscle damage or your edema
right but maybe the ones that are pink
are the ones that sense your anabolic
hormones testosterone
insulin-like growth factor one which is
another highly anabolically associated
hormone and then the ones in black look
at things like metabolic stress
uh hypoxia lactate we know lactate is a
pretty potent signal of muscle growth
same thing right so we understand quite
a bit now that there are different ways
we can signal the muscle to grow and
it's probably all these different things
so if we come back and take a look at a
summary slide i had in part one
if you're seeing this and you're like
what is all this go back and watch part
one
but my basic point is this even saying
the term muscle hypertrophy
is a little bit not specific because
there are different ways your muscle can
grow
and so while we are starting to
understand more and more about what
parts of the tissue and a part of the
the cells actually grow and why what we
don't know
yet is if different types of training
cause different types of hypertrophy
so the classic example here and this is
the short version is you have
contractile hypertrophy versus
sarcoplasmic hypertrophy so the elements
that contract in your muscle that cause
force
increasing versus sarcoplasm which would
be the non-contractile elements so
perhaps
some type of training causes the muscle
to grow in a way that would
allow it to also produce more force
perhaps other types of training cause it
to grow in a method
that increases the size but doesn't
necessarily mean it can contract with
any more force
if that even happens we're not sure and
so then we're certainly not sure at all
about how the stimuli would differ right
so why is it this rep range causes this
type of
uh adaptation and this rep range causes
this type of adaptation we aren't
anywhere close to knowing
the answers to those things so we know
it's got to be a stimuli thing right
they're clearly getting different
signals but what how do those signals
differ
is one may be working with
mechanoreceptors and another working
with
the hypoxia we don't know any of that
stuff yet so
more information to learn and i guess a
new video for me to make
five or ten years from now whenever we
get that information if we ever
do okay so let's assume though
regardless
somehow you successfully completed step
one and you induced
some sort of signal from there our
cascade is a little bit more clear in
terms of what has to happen
you have to go on to step two which is
what we call our signaling cascade okay
now this happens in the cytoplasm so the
cytoplasm is
inside of the cell sarcolemma being the
wall
cytoplasm being inside and this happens
through a whole bunch of molecules that
we call signaling proteins so these
signaling molecules are an entire
host of different protein whose job is
to communicate some sort of signal from
the cell wall
which we now know to actually really be
these receptors
all the way through the cytoplasm and to
the nucleus so you can tell
your cell how to respond so before we
talk about these in more detail let's
look at what that actually means because
i remember as a student
hearing this term protein and and not
really understanding what it meant and i
thought i did but i would be still
confused i'm like
you told me this is a protein how is
this a protein etc so i want to look at
what that phrase even means to begin
with
and you have to realize you have a whole
host of different types of proteins in
your body now
we as exercise scientists and stuff tend
to think of
the structural ones so we think of
protein we think of actin we think of
myosin and those are build up proteins
sure but you also have to realize all of
your enzymes are proteins
all of your receptors so the things i'm
talking about these receptors on the
cell wall they're all
also made of protein your antibodies
your neuropeptides all that stuff these
are all made of proteins
so some really helpful examples you can
see at the bottom there you probably
remember keratin
that's the thing that makes up your hair
and nails that's a protein
right hemoglobin the thing that carries
all the oxygen in your blood
is a protein insulin you know what that
does right pepsin which is kind of a
digestive
well not kind of it is a digestive these
are all different proteins in fact you
have about a hundred thousand
different types of proteins in your body
so if we come back to this slide
these specific set of proteins and then
there's a whole bunch of them there's
thousands of them
their job is to convey a signal so we
collectively call them signaling
proteins so that's what that phrase
means so again
what it would look like they sit there
one one of them anyways sits right next
to the cell wall
sees hey the cell wall has been
stretched or it's been
there's been hypoxia or there's been
damage there or there's been contraction
or there's lactate bound there or
testosterone is found there or
any of the things we just got done
talking about that cause the signal to
happen
it would see that in the receptor the
receptor would hit that protein if you
will that protein would hit another
protein
protein and protein protein and those
things would cascade all the way down
to the nucleus okay we would call that
the anabolic
signaling cascade and probably the most
famous one
is called mtor and that's one particular
protein that we know is very highly
associated
with muscle anabolism or muscle
hypertrophy
okay now we're learning more and more
about mtor and all the details of it
later but again i'll just simply say at
this point it is highly associated
with the anabolic process okay
so once you've activated all those
proteins and then one protein activated
another one and then another one
activated mtor and that activated
another one
eventually one of them would hit the
nucleus and that's the part of the cell
that holds your dna
and that's important because that's
what's going to tell your cell to grow
shrink die repair whatever else it wants
it to do
so within the nucleus like i said you've
got your dna this is the stuff you
inherited from mom and dad
so you may have the dna to code for a
whole host of different proteins
how do you code for those proteins how
do you start building them well it
depends on what signal has been
transduced
to the nucleus right so this is why this
cascade is so important
right now going into this a little bit
more detail um
because it's actually kind of fun so i i
kind of outlined one's
signaling cascade but there's a couple
of other general categories i think you
should be aware of
so i talked about this anabolic one and
it's typically the anabolic cascade is
more specifically the the p13k akt mtor1
so there's a bunch of different proteins
along that so one activates another one
activates another one down there
well we also have a catabolic cascade
right so you have to have some signal to
grow
you're also going to have some signal
that says hey break some tissue down
uh that could happen because say the the
muscle cell is damaged because you're
lifting and you want to break it down
and get rid of all the
the non-functioning proteins and the
things that have been misshaped and
misfold
well that's has to be a catabolic
process right and so you can see the
foxo
um the nf alphabet that that's a very
common
catabolic cascade as well
and then you also have something in the
middle which is a little bit more fun
which is an inhibitor so now this is a
cascade it's not anabolic
it doesn't cause a muscle to grow it's
not catabolic either it doesn't cause
you to break down
but it's an inhibitor so what its job is
to block the anabolic process
this is very very very very important
because unblocked
tissue growth is cancer that's
a tumor right so you want to be able to
grow tissue but you also want to be able
to say oh okay let's i want to stop
growth in this case there's too much
going on
that's not necessarily the same thing as
just breaking down the current tissue
it's blocking the growth process
so it's a very important break you have
on that gas pedal if you will
and by far the most common or most
famous or infamous one
is called myostatin okay and in fact you
can see
you can google around and see more and
more photos but we've seen now plenty of
animals
and there are humans if you're wondering
who are born
without the genes to code for the
myostatin protein
and so you can see what happens to these
folks these are not animals that have
beginnings
been given steroids they're not been
given uh special antibiotics or
something like that they just naturally
had a mutation their
x-men if you will right we all have
mutations right so
some mutations make you have different
eye color and maybe grow taller than
your mom or whatever it happens to be
well their mutation happened to be they
didn't have the gene or enough of the
gene to program for enough
of the protein to build enough myostatin
and so they weren't able to check
muscle growth enough and so they get
huge so you can see roger the
kangaroo there the the famous cow and
the bull evil
the dog there so that's what myostatin
would do
of course you may be thinking wait a
minute can i then buy myostatin
inhibitors
mmm i'll let you look into that maybe
maybe not
maybe it's legal maybe it's not legal
maybe they're legal but they don't work
i'll leave it up to you okay
that's what signaling cascade really is
so if we come back here we've got our
nucleus our next step then step
three is that gene expression process so
the
signaling has happened the dna has to go
there now to give you a very quick
review
of again your basic biology here
gene expression means this you all know
you have you know like what is it
three billion base pairs right and
you've got around 20
000 different genes in your body what is
a gene per se
well gene is just a sequence of dna or
rna in this case mostly dna
that encodes the synthesis of a specific
rna product
in other words this chunk of the dna
codes for this particular protein
all right so what it could look like is
this
you know that the atgc thing right and
those are all your nucleotide base pairs
so
in this particular example you can see
that say
uh ata ata comes together what that
means is
when you replicate ata from your rna
then you coded for a particular amino
acid called
i okay great so you take your nucleotide
base pairs you replicate them
you make a whole bunch of amino acids
you take those amino acids put them
together
a bunch of those you call that a peptide
you take a bunch of those peptides
together and now you've got a protein
all right and so that's what i'm really
showing you here so the eventual
combination of the amino acids makes the
protein
and the red red sequences you're seeing
here would be the gene
so you can imagine these line of code
just running running running running
running running around here
well this particular sequence the red to
red is a whole bunch of
nucleotides that then code for a whole
bunch of very specific amino acids
and that very specific amino acid
sequence makes a very specific
protein okay so that's how you can go
into your dna and say hey
we need to build this protein and they
can say okay i know the line of code to
start with and to stop with
to build the specific amount and
sequence
in other words order of amino acids to
get that protein you want
and there you go okay so it would look
like this
and you have your dna you go through
this transcription process which makes
it into rna but eventually you make some
amino acids
and then from there you combine those
into making your appropriate protein so
i know i cut a lot of stuff out of that
i'm just trying to give you that quick
reminder and so you let you visualize
and see it a little bit
of how the process works so a really
really interesting paper just came out
uh this year i believe um stu phillips
was a part of that
but his large amount of authors and they
ran just an incredible amount of
um really high level science on this
stuff and found that
they believe there's about 141 different
genes that are now associated with
muscle growth so in order to grow your
muscle it doesn't just come from one
it's about 140 and that's actually
pretty awesome because
that list could have been a whole lot
higher now that we know that we can
start doing more targeted therapies to
just see if we can activate those gene
sequences specifically more
or less but really really really cool
stuff so again 20 000 genes or whatever
you have nobody really knows
probably only about 140 of those are
responsible for
all your games
if you want here's an actual image of
them so it's a really nice
thing i'm not going to walk you through
this video but they also show you what
happens kind of with aging to those
genes and this little sensitivity and
then some other stuff so
really impressive work by that group
nice job
so now that you understand step three
let's move on to step four
okay you've activated the genes your 441
different ones are going
and now we actually have to synthesize
the protein and that happens in the
ribosome
most specifically so if you're
unfamiliar with that those are a whole
bunch of other little organelle within
your body
and this is basically their job is
protein synthesis so they would kind of
come on the back end of the nucleus and
say okay you want to replicate these
genes
got it you go through the process we
just got done describing but we're the
ones that are going to actually build
the proteins
so let's imagine this you had a protein
over here
that you want to grow let's call that
myosin so if you remember from part one
the first video in this series that's
kind of what a myosin would look like
and the myosin is one of the
myofilaments in your in your
muscles right and you want to grow that
you want to make that thing larger okay
great you did the stimulus you got the
protein cascade going you got the dna
expression
and now you're trying to build that
protein this is what it would look like
all right and this would be your protein
synthesis process you would take
those amino acids whatever they happen
to be you would ship them to the
ribosomes the ribosomes would then start
combining them together
and it would spit out that particular
protein and so it would start doing this
okay great continue to feed me amino
acids and i will continue to take these
things
and build them together into your whole
functioning protein and so
the size of that myosin then continues
to grow and grow and grow
as long as you feed it amino acids
in step three or part three rather of
these videos i will talk about what
specific foods that needs to be
what type of amino acids etc etc to
maximize
that right so if you do the right if you
redo the right training
you'll maximize steps one through three
or four
and if you have the right nutrients then
step four will also be able to be
maximized all right again just to show
you some fun stuff here
you can see in the column kind of on the
edge there different amino acid
sequences in this particular one
that's what myosin looks like right so
it is that specific amino acid sequence
that you'll get to build that particular
protein
okay we also need to talk a little bit
about overall protein balance because we
tend to assume that if you're going
through proteins synthesis that you're
growing more muscle
you're getting bigger and that's not the
case so we have to understand is what we
call overall protein balance
so at all times your body is doing a
little bit of protein synthesis and it's
also doing a little bit of protein
breakdown
so what you care about is what's the
balance so if i'm gaining 5 but i'm
losing 10
my net is actually negative 5. not good
or the opposite here right
so we see different scenarios that could
happen
right you can see that the first section
over there and i'm not going to walk you
through the basic map but you get the
idea here right
so we need to focus on not only
maximizing protein synthesis but also
then minimizing protein breakdown so
that our overall
balance is where we want it to be okay
now where you can get tricked you can
see products
and commercials and other
marketing schemes that'll say things
like we have scientifically measured our
supplement
and it does this with protein synthesis
and you're like great then there's no
way it doesn't cause me to grow muscle
but if they don't describe you what
happened on the breakdown side of it
then you don't know at all what your
balance could look like so be very wary
of those things when you're like wait a
minute i thought
hmb didn't work but yet here's another
clinical trial showing that it increased
protein synthesis by 40
ah but did they measure protein
breakdown no they didn't well then i
don't really know what's going to
actually happen to my overall tissue
and the vast majority of studies will
not measure protein breakdown
and fair enough it's pretty difficult to
do protein synthesis is pretty easy to
measure
but nonetheless something to keep in
mind so
i'm visually depicting a really a fairly
famous
review article that came out about 20
years ago now and what they said is all
right let me present to you some
different scenarios and i want you to
tell me whether or not that scenario
would be
a net result in muscle hypertrophy so
growth and gains
anabolic or net results in atrophy or
catabolic or
muscle loss and our first scenario is
this
so as you sit there at rest what's
happening are you growing muscle
are you losing muscle turns out
at rest you're fairly catabolic
right so you're actually going down the
wrong direction right after immediately
after
say the most perfectly designed strength
training valve for hypertrophy
you're still actually pretty negative
well you're negative overall now what's
interesting is
was the stimulus anabolic yes because it
moved you more towards the anabolic but
in and of itself wasn't enough to get
you into a net
positive balance and that's again the
trickery there right so it was anabolic
it moved you
up closer but it wasn't enough to put
you over the threshold of net
positive balance what about just protein
alone if you just had a high protein
meal
well it turns out that is a pretty
potent anabolic signal and so it will
move you there and what's nice about
that is these signals
from strength training as well as
proteins seem to be additive
right and so what i mean is the bump you
get from resistance exercise combined
with the separate bump from protein
means you're really really high in the
anabolic window so
it's pretty clear that you need to have
some protein around when that signal is
there
to maximize your growth that doesn't
mean per se you have to have
your protein shake immediately after
your workout but you need to have amino
acids available when that signal
that molecular signal that gene
expression that protein synthesis signal
are high
if they're if they're high and you have
no supply you're not going to grow
if they then die down and then you
finally bring the supply in you're
minimizing your window you're not
maximizing your gains
well it turns out if you had
carbohydrate to that list
you go even higher up the scale and so
it's pretty clear that the vast majority
of time you're going to be recommended
to have protein and carbohydrate around
to maximize muscle growth
and in fact even because of this just to
complete the picture
protein and carbohydrate alone
independent of the strength training
would be there so it's no surprise for
decades and decades that bodybuilders
trying to maximize their growth
are going to do their strength training
have protein and carbohydrate not only
around their workout but then also
as much as they can throughout the day
now i do have a separate video entirely
on the post exercise anabolic window
i think it's a 25 minute version so you
can go check that out if you want more
detail there so i'm not going to waste
your time
here but the kind of highlighter take
home point there increases in synthesis
following
amino acid feeding only happens if the
essential amino acids are ingested
so this slide i just showed you is
assuming we're talking about essential
amino acids
right this is not going to come from
eating broccoli it's not going to come
from eating
low quality protein sources you've got
to have the essential amino acids and
specifically
leucine threshold has to be hit
okay now another thing we need to keep
in mind here as well
is i described this in video one but to
come
into it shortly here we have a little
bit of what i call a scaling problem
so be very careful because the amount of
acute protein synthesis or mps
is not going to actually match the
amount of actual muscle growth
so if you looked at a study or something
you found wow eating
tacos after a workout increased protein
synthesis by 30
you will not see then 30 growth in your
muscle
it doesn't work like that in fact the
number is probably significantly lower
so you can't really take things and say
okay this one had
a higher rate of muscle protein
synthesis and then guarantee
it will equal a higher amount of muscle
growth
so those numbers don't match up now
generally if something has a higher
acute protein synthesis rate we assume
it would lead to a higher amount of
muscle growth eventually but that
doesn't always
in fact very rarely does that lead out
that does that end up being true
so be very careful when interpreting
things like that
into actual eventual muscle growth
all right so to kind of summarize what i
just got done talking about there
if you want to add muscle mass you have
to do the following
number one you have to train there has
to be some sort of signal and we talked
about the different ways
stress tension or damage right
why do you have to train because you
have to give yourself and your tissue a
reason to grow
okay then you also have to eat right but
in order to that reason to grow you have
to
initially you have to to have a strong
enough signal to go through all three
parts of that signal and cascade
so protein signaling gene expression and
protein synthesis so
say you did a type of training and it
was enough to start mtor activation
but it wasn't really enough to convince
your nucleus to replicate the gene
then you're not going to grow or maybe
you were enough to do that but you
weren't really enough to convince the
ribosomes to finish the protein
synthesis process
then you're not going to grow or you're
not going to grow as maximally as
possible
well none of that matters if you don't
eat sufficiently either
right so why do you have to eat well you
have to have the fuel for two things
number one you have to have the fuel to
power the training and that's mostly
going to come from carbohydrates right
strength training is powered not by
protein
clearly right protein is a poor energy
source it's not really by fat so
carbohydrates are your fuel for your
training session
and then you also have to fuel the
growth process
so remember when you break apart a bond
and chemically that typically releases
energy not always but usually
so when you want to put a bond together
like you want to go through protein
synthesis you want to take amino acids
and put them together
that requires you investing energy so
that
that part also requires energy and that
comes also from carbohydrate
so if you don't have sufficient
carbohydrate around it's very difficult
to then go through the actual cellular
process of protein
synthesis and maybe i'll say this
differently i can't promise you that
say somebody in a ketogenic diet they
still can go through protein synthesis
no doubt about it i just know that you
can go through it a lot
faster with a high amount of
carbohydrate around
and so again the the assumption with all
these videos is you're trying to
maximize muscle growth not what's the
minimum
possible to keep some muscle around
that's not really what i'm after
and then number two so you have to eat
you have because you have to have the
fuel but then you have to have the
building material so none of that stuff
matters you have an epic signal
you the right kind of training your
protein synthesis is ready to go
you've got all kinds of fuel but you
don't have the amino acids available
then there's nothing to put together and
synthesize and especially the essential
amino acids
so if we put this together in one visual
picture here's what it would look like
and i'm going to summarize all of your
exercise physiology class in like one
minute okay
so let's say you had some carbohydrate
no it doesn't matter that it's grain
i've just
picked a random picture of carbohydrates
right we know that eventually those get
broken down in your stomach as glucose
from there you're going to
make it transfer that into some or break
that down metabolically and do acetyl
coa
as a result you give off some carbon
dioxide that acetylcoat goes onto the
krebs cycle you lose a little bit of co2
but you gain what we call atp
atp is in split into adp and pi and as a
result that gives off heat
and some energy you use that energy on
the myosin head
part one to cause some contraction
and the muscles moved okay you made that
contraction
and that resulted in some sort of
stimulus we've already got done talking
about that a lot right
so on the wall the cell wall you've got
some sort of stimulus
that activated one particular protein
and activated another protein that
activated another protein
and we called that the signaling cascade
that then spoke to the nucleus and told
the nucleus
okay express the genes you have to build
the protein
for myosin so then you went through that
protein synthesis process
and you went from there now in order to
complete that process though you had to
consume some protein
now again i know there's fat and salmon
don't get off track here folks
so you take that amino acid that you ate
and you don't go through that acetyl-coa
and krebs cycle thing
because we don't use protein free energy
you use that amino acid to just
ship it to the tissue as supply so now
that the amino acids are available when
you're going through that protein
synthesis process you can take them
slowly start to add them to your myosin
chain and eventually
that tissue and that muscle in this case
gets larger
all right if you do that properly you'll
go from your skinny little self
to your new magnified and jacked itself
and you'll have increased
most likely the diameter the amount of
myofilaments but certainly the diameter
of the muscle fiber now part one
of this series videos described all that
process in detail about what actually is
growing larger in the muscle cell
but you get it by now okay
now step five if you've done
all of that right everything has come
together
the last thing you have to accomplish to
grow muscle
is some sort of magic i don't know um
perhaps pay off some like
shaman or a voodoo god to create some
sort of hex or make some sort of spell
and then just hope to the heavens that
you grow muscle because
i don't know right i know some of you
are thinking
yep i've tried like hell to grow muscle
i can't
it's all about step five for me well hey
i feel you i guess
but hire a new shaman the one you got
sucks fire
okay so to kind of finish up what we're
talking about here
what are the recommendations we can give
because i wasn't going to make you watch
the whole video and not give you
some training recommendations here's
what you basically have to do
you've got to hit one of those big three
stimuli right
tension stress or damage at least
once to three times per week per muscle
group okay
video three i'll talk about the volume
how many reps all that type of stuff
and then in terms of food you have to be
an overall caloric surplus okay
and then you have to have sufficient
protein which you can see there if you
do all those things
you got a shot to maximizing your muscle
group now that we've finished our
discussion of
what we know scientifically about how
the muscle actually grows
what actually causes it what signal is
it what stimulates it
it's finally time for us to get to part
three how do i train how do i eat to
maximize the girl
i appreciate you staying along for this
ride i know you've all been dying in
fact most of you probably aren't even
listening to this because you just
skipped to part three
but that's okay i know that i'm special
there's only a few amount of us real
physiology and muscle physiology nerds
out there so
those 600 of you that watch this or
something part one and part two
i got a lot of love for you all right
and to the three million they're gonna
watch part three
whatever learn some science i'm out of
here
[Music]
you